<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC 
	"-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>AGIV Java Security Design</title>
		<subtitle>
			Highlights the architecture and design of the AGIV Java
			Security framework.
		</subtitle>
		<subtitle>
			Version &project.version;
		</subtitle>
		<copyright>
			<year>2011-2012</year>
			<holder>AGIV</holder>
		</copyright>
		<releaseinfo>24 March 2012</releaseinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Frank</firstname>
				<surname>Cornelis</surname>
				<email>info@e-contract.be</email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<abstract>
			<para>
				In this document we describe the architectural choices behind
				the AGIV Java Security framework.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</articleinfo>

	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The
			<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
			component plays a central role within the framework. An
			<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
			instance corresponds with a certain user credential (e.g.
			username/password). This component basically decorates vanilla JAX-WS
			stubs with different JAX-WS SOAP handlers to add the required AGIV
			security behavior. Each provided JAX-WS SOAP handler implements a
			different part of a WS-* specification. The framework comes with
			different clients for the IP-STS, R-STS and secure conversations that
			are required by the
			<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
			component for acquiring the security tokens. The
			<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
			component can also handle HTTP/SOCKS network proxies.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Dependencies</title>
			<para>
				During the AGIV Java Security framework development we tried to
				use as less dependencies as possible. This in order to avoid runtime
				conflicts with the different web service stacks as much as possible.
				We could have used for example the Apache CXF STSClient, but this
				would have introduced Apache CXF as dependency. Basically we only
				want to depend on the JAX-WS API. Of course certain operations, like
				the creation of the different WS-Security XML signatures, require us
				to include specific dependencies like Apache WSS4J. All used
				dependencies also run on Java 5.
			</para>
			<para>
				For logging we use Apache Commons Logging.
			</para>
			<para>
				The AGIV Java Security framework has been tested under both
				Apache WSS4J version 1.6.4 and 1.6.5. Apache WSS4J version 1.6.5 is
				using Apache XML Security 1.5.1 which has a much stricter Id
				resolution policy. This might conflict at run-time with other
				libraries that use Apache XML Security to create/verify XML
				signatures. For this reason we bundle the AGIV Java Security
				framework with Apache WSS4J version 1.6.4.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Token Caching</title>
			<para>
				The
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				component takes care of the caching of the different tokens. A
				security token is represented in Java using the
				<code>SecurityToken</code>
				class.
			</para>
			<para>
				Each
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				instance caches its IP-STS token.
			</para>
			<para>
				Each
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				instance caches the R-STS tokens on a per web service location
				basis.
			</para>
			<para>
				Each
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				instance caches the secure conversation tokens (if applicable) on a
				per web service location basis.
			</para>
			<para>
				The
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				component will reacquire a token at a certain time before it
				expires. This time before expiration is configurable at the
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				level.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Multi-threading</title>
			<para>
				JAX-WS is inherently not multi-threaded by specification. However,
				an
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				component instance can be shared between different threads. The
				multi-threaded support has been achieved without the usage of
				synchronization monitors by using
				<code>ConcurrentHashMap</code>
				as much as possible for the implementation of the different token
				caches.
			</para>
			<para>
				The STS clients use JAX-WS themselves to request security tokens
				from the different STS based services. As such the STS clients are
				not thread-safe as per the JAX-WS specification. The
				<code>AGIVSecurity</code>
				component itself thus uses different STS client instances when
				acquiring a certain security token.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>STS Clients</title>
			<para>
				There is an STS client for each STS service:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						IP-STS to acquire a security token based on user credentials.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						R-STS to acquire security tokens based on IP-STS security
						tokens that apply to a certain AGIV web service.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Secure conversation contexts that are required by
						WS-SecureConversation enabled AGIV web service.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Although JAX-WS 2.1 comes with WS-Addressing support, the
				different STS clients have their own WS-Addressing implementation.
				This was done in order to avoid a runtime conflict when Apache Axis2
				is used on a Java 6 JRE.
			</para>
			<para>
				Each STS client is specifically tailored for its corresponding
				AGIV security policy. The STS clients do not interpret the WS-Policy
				and WS-SecurityPolicy at runtime. As such the STS client
				implementation is strongly linked with this AGIV security policy.
				Changes in the AGIV security policy will most likely require changes
				within the different STS clients.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>AGIV Security Protocol</title>
		<para>
			In this section we analyze the AGIV Security Protocol. The
			analysis only highlights the most relevant cryptographic properties
			of the protocol. As such protocol details that do not impact the
			security properties are not mentioned.
		</para>
		<para>
			We first define a simple formal protocol notation. The syntax is
			similar to that of the BAN logic. We do not formalize the believes
			and possessions of each party participating in a protocol run.
		</para>
		<para>
			Principal A sends to principal B a message M:
		</para>
		<para>
			A &rarr; B : M
		</para>
		<para>
			Principal A sends to principal B messages M
			<subscript>1</subscript>
			and M
			<subscript>2</subscript>
			:
		</para>
		<para>
			A &rarr; B : M
			<subscript>1</subscript>
			, M
			<subscript>2</subscript>
		</para>
		<para>
			Principal A sends to principal B a message M over an SSL secured
			connection:
		</para>
		<para>
			A &rarr;
			<subscript>SSL</subscript>
			B : M
		</para>
		<para>Message M is encrypted with symmetric key K:</para>
		<para>
			{M}
			<subscript>K</subscript>
		</para>
		<para>
			Message M is encrypted with public key K
			<superscript>+</superscript>
			of principal A
			:
		</para>
		<para>
			{M}
			<subscript>
				K
				<superscript>+</superscript>
				<subscript>A</subscript>
			</subscript>
		</para>
		<para>
			Message M is signed with symmetric key K:
		</para>
		<para>
			sign
			<subscript>K</subscript>
			(M)
		</para>
		<para>
			The algorithm for such symmetric key signatures is
			HMAC-SHA1.
		</para>
		<para>
			Message M is signed with the private key of principal A:
		</para>
		<para>
			sign
			<subscript>
				K
				<superscript>-</superscript>
				<subscript>A</subscript>
			</subscript>
			(M)
		</para>
		<section id="section-ip-sts-username">
			<title>IP-STS with Username/password credentials</title>
			<para>
				The relying party (RP) starts by sending a message to the
				IP-STS. This message contains the credentials and some entropy
				value.
			</para>
			<para>
				RP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				IP-STS : username, password, Ent
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, AppliesTo
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
			</para>
			<para>
				The IP-STS answers with a token and some entropy value:
			</para>
			<para>
				IP-STS &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP : Ent
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				, Token
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
			</para>
			<para>
				Where the token actually is:
			</para>
			<para>
				Token
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				= {Token'}
				<subscript>K</subscript>
				, {K}
				<subscript>
					K
					<superscript>+</superscript>
					<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				</subscript>
			</para>
			<para>
				With K a symmetric AES key and K
				<superscript>+</superscript>
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				the public RSA key of R-STS. So only the R-STS can read the value of
				Token'. The relying party itself cannot read the content of Token'.
			</para>
			<para>
				From the Ent
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				and Ent
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				entropy values both parties calculate a secret.
			</para>
			<para>
				K
				<subscript>POP IP-STS</subscript>
				= PSHA1(Ent
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, Ent
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				)
			</para>
			<para>
				The PSHA1 algorithm is defined as part of the SSL
				specifications. This secret is later on used as proof-of-possession
				(POP) for the acquired IP-STS security token.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>R-STS</title>
			<para>
				The relying party sends the IP-STS security token together with
				a proof-of-possession signature to the R-STS.
			</para>
			<para>
				RP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				R-STS : Token
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				, T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, sign
				<subscript>
					K
					<subscript>POP IP-STS</subscript>
				</subscript>
				(T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				), AppliesTo
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
			</para>
			<para>
				The relying party indicates that the requested security token should
				apply to a certain service provide (SP). The relying party is not
				signing the IP-STS security token, but the timestamp T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				.
				This allows the R-STS to believe that the relying party recently
				said that it indeed wants to use the corresponding security token
				for accessing a certain web service.
			</para>
			<para>
				The R-STS can decrypt the security token because the token has
				been encrypted with the private key of R-STS.
			</para>
			<para>
				The R-STS answers with a new security token and a corresponding
				proof key.
			</para>
			<para>
				R-STS &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP : Token
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				, K
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Secure Conversation</title>
			<para>
				For AGIV web services that use WS-SecureConversation the
				relying party needs to create a secure conversation before being
				able to invoke a business web service.
			</para>
			<section>
				<title>Acquiring a secure conversation token</title>
				<para>
					The relying party sends the following message to a service
					provider SP:
				</para>
				<para>
					RP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					SP :
					Token
					<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
					, T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					, sign
					<subscript>
						K
						<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
					</subscript>
					(T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					),
					Ent
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
				</para>
				<para>
					Where Ent
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					is a new entropy value generated by the relying party and T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					is also a new timestamp value generated by the relying party.
				</para>
				<para>
					The service provider answers with:
				</para>
				<para>
					SP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					RP :
					Token
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
					, Ent
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
				</para>
				<para>
					Where Token
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
					is the secure conversation token.
				</para>
				<para>
					Both relying party and service provider calculate a secret
					out
					of the entropy values:
				</para>
				<para>
					K
					<subscript>POP SP</subscript>
					= PSHA1(Ent
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					, Ent
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
					)
				</para>
				<para>
					This secret is later used as proof-of-possession (POP) for the
					acquired secure conversation token.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Using a secure conversation token</title>
				<para>
					The relying party can invoke a business web service using the
					secure conversation token.
				</para>
				<para>
					RP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					SP : M,
					Token
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
					,
					T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					,
					sign
					<subscript>
						K
						<subscript>POP SP</subscript>
					</subscript>
					(T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					)
				</para>
				<para>
					Where M is the payload for the business web service request and T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					is a new timestamp generated by the relying party.
				</para>
				<para>
					The business web service answers with some response message
					M'.
				</para>
				<para>
					SP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					RP : M'
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Cancelling a secure conversation token</title>
				<para>
					After invoking the business web service the relying party can
					cancel the secure conversation token.
				</para>
				<para>
					RP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					SP :
					Token
					<subscript>SP</subscript>
					, T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					,
					sign
					<subscript>
						K
						<subscript>POP SP</subscript>
					</subscript>
					(T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					)
				</para>
				<para>
					Where T
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
					is a new timestamp generated by the relying party.
				</para>
				<para>
					The service provider acknowledges the operation.
				</para>
				<para>
					SP &rarr;
					<subscript>SSL</subscript>
					RP: ack
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>SAML secured web services</title>
			<para>
				Not every AGIV web service requires a WS-SecureConversation to
				operate. In this case the web service simply requires the R-STS SAML
				token for authentication/authorization.
			</para>
			<para>
				The relying party sends the following message to a service
				provider SP:
			</para>
			<para>
				RP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				SP :
				M, Token
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				, T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, sign
				<subscript>
					K
					<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				</subscript>
				(T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				)
			</para>
			<para>
				Where M is the payload for the business web service request and T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				is a new timestamp value generated by the relying party.
			</para>
			<para>
				The business web service answers with some response message
				M'.
			</para>
			<para>
				SP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP : M'
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>WS-Addressing</title>
			<para>
				The WS-Addressing adds the following to each request message:
			</para>
			<para>
				RP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				SP : N
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, A
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
				, L
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
				, ...
			</para>
			<para>
				Where N
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				is a nonce generated by the relying party, A
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
				is the action that the relying party wants to invoke on the service
				provider, and L
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
				is the location of the service provider.
			</para>
			<para>
				The service provider relates the response with the request by
				echoing the nonce N
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				in the response message.
			</para>
			<para>
				SP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP: N
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, ...
			</para>
			<para>
				This mechanism prevents replay attacks and ensures
				recognizability of the messages towards the service provider.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>WS-Security timestamp</title>
			<para>
				The service provider adds a timestamp to each response message.
			</para>
			<para>
				SP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP: T
				<subscript>SP</subscript>
				, ...
			</para>
			<para>
				Besides message freshness, the yielded cryptographic properties
				of this timestamp are less clear given the reply attack
				countermeasure provided by the WS-Addressing and the fact that the
				security tokens have a limited lifetime anyway.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>IP-STS with certificate credentials</title>
			<para>
				The IP-STS service also support X509 certificates as user
				credential. The relying party (RP) starts by sending a message to
				the IP-STS. This message contains the certificate and a signature
				using the corresponding private key.
			</para>
			<para>
				RP &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				IP-STS : Cert
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, Ent
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				, AppliesTo
				<subscript>R-STS</subscript>
				,
				sign
				<subscript>
					K
					<superscript>-</superscript>
					<subscript>RP</subscript>
				</subscript>
				(L
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				, T
				<subscript>RP</subscript>
				)
			</para>
			<para>
				The signature signs the location of the IP-STS service and a
				timestamp generated by the relying party. The message also contains
				some entropy value generated by the relying party.
			</para>
			<para>
				The IP-STS answers with a token and some entropy value:
			</para>
			<para>
				IP-STS &rarr;
				<subscript>SSL</subscript>
				RP : Ent
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
				, Token
				<subscript>IP-STS</subscript>
			</para>
			<para>
				Further behaviour is already described under
				<xref linkend="section-ip-sts-username" />
				.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<appendix>
		<title>AGIV Java Security Design License</title>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="cc-30-by-nc-nd.png"
						scale="100" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			This document has been released under the
			<ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons 3.0</ulink>
			license.
		</para>
	</appendix>

	<appendix>
		<title>Revision history</title>
		<table>
			<title>Revision history</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colwidth="2*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Date</entry>
						<entry>Author</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>8 Jan 2012</entry>
						<entry>Frank Cornelis</entry>
						<entry>Initial version.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>29 Jan 2012</entry>
						<entry>Frank Cornelis</entry>
						<entry>X509 credentials.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>24 Mar 2012</entry>
						<entry>Frank Cornelis</entry>
						<entry>Optional WS-SecureConversation.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</appendix>
</article>
